So now we have our contracts in here and our code is compiling successfully.
现在我们有了我们的合约，并且我们的代码已经成功编译
We're probably going Want to deploy our code?
接下来我们要做的是部署我们的代码
Now in our last section, I know we use the scripts module.
在上一节中，我们用的是脚本模块
And we made our own manual deploy script.
并且创建了一个手动部署脚本
However, something that you'd notice, the more that you work with just raw ethers, or even just hard hat
然而，你可能会注意到，当你使用原生 ethers 或仅仅是 Hardhat 进行工作时
is that keeping track of all our deployments can get a little bit tricky.
跟踪所有部署会是一件棘手的事情
If you just use a deploy script,
如果你只使用一个部署脚本
it's not saving our deployments to any file.
它就不会把我们的部署保存到文件中去
Additionally, having everything in the deploy script for deploying
此外，把所有部署都放到一个部署脚本中
can make the tests and the deploy scripts, maybe not work exactly hand in hand.
可能会使测试和部署脚本之间无法完全兼容
And there are a couple of other things that might be a little bit tricky to work on,
而且还可能会遇到一些其他比较麻烦的事
we're actually going to work with a package
我们会使用一个包
that makes everything I just mentioned, and a couple other things way easier.
它会使我刚才提到的所有事情还有一些其他事情变得更容易一些
And this package that I'm talking about is going to be the hard hat deploy package.
而我所说的这个包就是 "hardhat-deploy" 包
There's a link to this package in the GitHub repository associated with this course.
这个包的链接也会放到课程关联的 GitHub 仓库里
It's a hardhat plugin for replicable deployments and easy testing.
它是一个用于可复制部署及简便测试的 Hardhat 插件
And if we scroll down to installation, we can see we install it basically the normal way.
如果我们向下滑到安装部分，就能看到可以用通用方法安装它
They're using npm. And we're gonna go ahead and use yarn.
他们用的是 npm 而我们还是会继续使用 yarn
So for us to add it, we'll do yarn, add hardhat dash deploy.
所以要想添加它，就要执行 "yarn add hardhat-deploy"
And then of course, we're gonna do dash dash Dev.
当然了，还有 "--dev"
Once done deploying this require statement to our hard hat.config.js.
一旦部署（口误，应为“安装”）完成，就需要在我们的 "hardhat.config.js" 中 "require" 进来
Once again, basically the config is our entry point.
再次强调，这个配置文件就是我们的入口点
This is where we're gonna get started.
基本上就是我们一切开始的地方
And we can go ahead and delete our deploy.js script.
然后我们就可以删除我们的 "deploy.js" 脚本了
Now if we run yarn hardhat, you see that we have a bunch of new tasks in here,
现在如果我们运行 "yarn hardhat"，你会看到这里有一堆新的 task
with one of them being this deploy task,
其中之一就是 "deploy" task
this deploy task is going to be the main task that we use to deploy our contracts.
这个 "deploy" task 将是我们部署合约时主要使用的 task
Instead of writing our deploy scripts in the Scripts folder,
这次我们不再在 "scripts" 文件夹中编写我们的部署脚本
we're actually going to create a new folder,
而是创建一个新的文件夹
we can create a new folder by just doing MK dir deploy.
我们可以使用 "mkdir deploy" 来新建文件夹
Or you can always right click and hit New Folder.
或者你也可以右键并点击新建文件夹("New Folder")
This deploy folder is going to be where a lot of hard hat Deploy Module looks to deploy code.
这个 "deploy" 文件夹将是许多 "hardhat-deploy" 模块部署代码的地方
And it's going to be where we are writing our scripts.
同时也是我们编写脚本的地方
To write our scripts, we usually need to add one more thing in here.
为了编写我们的脚本，通常还需要添加一个东西
Since we're going to be using ethers JS in all of our scripts,
因为我们要在所有脚本中使用 "ethers.js"
we want to add Hardhead deploy ethers to our package here.
所以我们要添加 "hardhat-deploy-ethers" 到我们的包里
Now, instead of just doing yarn, add dash dev hard at deploy ethers,
这回我们不再是只运行 "yarn --dev hardhat-deploy-ethers"
we're going to do something a little bit weird.
而是会做一些略显奇怪的事情
We're going to do yarn add or npm install dash dash Dev,
我们要运行 "yarn add" 或是 "npm install --dev"
and we're going to install it like this.
然后按照这样的方式来进行安装
So let me just copy this.
让我来复制一下这个东西
And you can just copy that from the repo.
你也可以直接从代码库里复制
And we'll do yarn, add dash dash Dev, and paste that in here.
然后我们来运行 "yarn add --dev" 并粘贴到这里
What we're doing is we're taking at nomic labs, hard hat ethers, which we've used before,
我们做的就是获取 "@nomiclabs/hardhat-ethers"，这是我们之前用过的
and we're overriding it with hard hat deploy ethers.
然后我们用 "hardhat-deploy-ehters" 把它覆盖掉
Remember how in our last project, we used hard hat ethers.
还记得我们在上个项目中是怎么做的么？我们使用的是 "hardhat-ethers"
So that hard hat could override ethers to use hard hat deploy.
所以 Hardhat 可以覆盖 ethers 使用 "hardhat-deploy"
(译者注：这句中的 hardhat-deploy 很可能应为 hardhat-ethers)
We use hard hat deploy ethers, so that hard hat deploy can override Hardhead,
我们使用了 "hardhat-deploy-ethers" 所以 "hardhat-deploy" 可以覆盖 Hardhat
which overrides ethers, which is kind of funny.
而它又覆盖了 ethers，这还挺有意思的
When you say like that, this will enable ethers to keep track of and remember
这样做的话 ethers 就能够跟踪并记住
all the different deployments that we actually make in our contract.
我们所部署的所有不同合约
So if we look at our package, JSON,
所以如果查看一下我们的 "package.json"
and now we can see our nomic labs dashboard had ethers.
现在我们就可以看到 "@nomiclabs/hardhat-ethers"
Now the version of it is going to be MPM. Hardhead deploy ethers.
现在它的版本是 "npm:hardhat-deploy-ethers"
This is our package dot JSON, basically saying
我们的 "package.json" 基本上就是在说
the hard hat ethers package is now overwritten by the hard hat deploy ethers package,
"hardhat-ethers" 包现在被 "hardhat-deploy-ethers" 包覆盖了
which is what we want.
这正是我们想要的
Alright, great. So now that we have that setup,
很好，现在我们已经做好了设置
we can start writing our deploy scripts,
那么就可以开始编写我们的部署脚本了
the way that Hart had to play works is
"hardhat-deploy" 的工作方式是
all the scripts that get added to our deploy folder will get run when we run yarn, hard hat deploy.
我们在 "deploy" 文件夹中添加的所有脚本都会在执行 "yarn hardhat deploy" 时运行
So a good practice is usually to number them
所以有一个很好的做法是对它们进行编号
so that they run in the order that you want them to run in.
以便让它们按照你想要的顺序运行
So since we only have one contract that we want to deploy the Funmi contract,
因为我们只有一个合约要部署，即 "FundMe" 合约
we're going to do 01 Deploy Funmi Jas,
所以我们就命名为 "01-deploy-fund-me.js"
and in this script, this is going to be where we define how to deploy the fundament contract.
在这个脚本中，我们将定义具体如何部署 "FundMe" 合约
Alright, so we're in our deploy Funmi scripts.
好的，现在在我们的 "deploy-fund-me" 脚本中
Now traditionally, what did we do,
通常情况下，我需要做哪些事情？
we did imports, we did the main function. And then we did calling of main function,
我们要导入库，还要定义 main 函数，并且要调用这个 main 函数
that Hardhead deploy is a little bit different,
"hardhat-deploy" 会有一点点不同
we're still going to import our libraries and packages,
我们仍然要导入所需的库和包
but we're not going to have main function.
但我们不再需要 main 函数了
And we're also not going to call the main function
当然也不再需要调用 main 函数了
when we run Hardhead deploy
当我们运行 "hardhat-deploy" 时
Harnett deploy is actually going to call a function that we specify. In this script here.
"hardhat-deploy" 实际上就是在调用我们指定的某个函数，这个脚本里的
What we're going to do is we're gonna create a function, we'll call it deploy funk.
我们要做的就是创建一个函数，命名为 "deployFunc"
We're going to export this deploy function as the default function for Hardhead deploy to look for,
我们要把这个 "deployFunc" 导出为 "hardhat-deploy" 默认要查找的函数
so we could say, module that exports dot default equals deploy funk.
因此我们要这么写 "module.exports.default = deployFunc"
To test it out, we can go ahead and do console dot log, hi.
要想测试它，我们使用 "console.log("Hi!")"
And then in our terminal, run yarn, hard hat, deploy.
然后在终端中运行 "yarn hardhat deploy"
Oops, get rid of the parentheses here. Sorry. Run it again.
哦，这里多了个括号，抱歉，再运行一次
And we can see it went and ran our deploy func here.
我们可以看到它运行了我们的 "deployFunc"
Now if this syntax is easier for you to understand,
如果你认为现在这种语法更易于你理解
go ahead and use this syntax
那么你可以继续使用这种语法
and we're going to be passing the heart at runtime environment as a parameter to this function.
我们将传入 “hardhat 运行环境”("hre")作为这个函数的输入参数
However, if we go to the heart hat deploy documentation,
然而，如果我们查看 "hardhat-deploy" 的文档
and we scroll down to an example script,
并向下滑到这个示例脚本
the syntax looks a little bit different.
这里使用的语法看起来会有些不同
And let me just explain what's going on here and how we're going to be writing ours.
我来解释一下这是什么意思，以及我们怎么使用这种方式编写
So instead of kind of defining everything like this,
与这里的定义方式不同
and defining the function name, similar to what we were doing before,
定义函数名时，和之前我们某次的做法类似
we're actually going to using a nameless, a synchronous function,
我们要使用一个无名的，异步函数
we're going to make it an anonymous function,
即，我们要把它创建为一个匿名函数
similar to what we've seen before.
就像我们之前见过的那样
So instead, we're going to say async parameters like this,
因此我们要写上 "async" 然后是参数，就像这样
I'm going to pass our parameters our heart at runtime environment in here.
我要在这里传入的参数是 “hardhat 运行环境”("hre")
And it's going to be an arrow function.
并且它是一个箭头函数
And then we're going to wrap this whole thing in module dot exports.
接着，我们要把这整个东西包装进 "module.exports" 里
So we're gonna say, module, dot exports, equals this async function like this.
所以我们要写成 "module.exports" 等于这个 async 函数，就像这样
This syntax here is nearly identical to what's up here,
这里的语法和上面的语法几乎是等价的
we just don't have a name for our async function.
只是我们的 async 函数没有名称罢了
So this is how we're going to set it up instead.
这就是我们要使用的配置方法
But if this syntax is a little bit confusing for you
但如果这种语法对你来说有点困惑
feel free to use this above as the two of these are going to be the same.
那么请自由使用上面那种，因为这两种方式是相同的
Now the next thing that most of the documentation does
现在，大多数文档的下一步做的都是
is it pulls out the variables and functions out of the HRV that we're going to use.
从 "hre" 中提取出我们要使用的变量和函数
HRV is the heart hat runtime environment.
"hre" 就是 “hardhat 运行环境”
Whenever we run a deploy script, heart hat deploy automatically calls this function
每当我们运行部署脚本时，"hardhat-deploy" 都会自动调用这个函数
and just passes the hard hat object into it
并将 hardhat 对象传递给它
similar to in back in hard hat simple storage. In our deploy script.
就像 hardhat 中的 "SimpleStorage" 一样，在我们的 "deploy" 脚本里
We had ethers run in network come from hard hat,
我们拥有 "ethers, run" 以及 "network" 来源是 "hardhat"
instead of coming from hard hat. We're coming from HRV,
这次不再是来源于 "hardhat" 而是 "hre"
which is basically the same thing as hard hat.
基本上它和 "hardhat" 是相同的
For our script, we're only going to use two variables from a jury
对我们的脚本来说，我们只使用 "hre" 中的两个变量
when you use const. Get named accounts. And deployments.
我们要使用 "const " 以及 "deployments"
This syntax might look a little bit weird for you.
这个语法对你来说可能会有些陌生
But it's just a way to pull these exact variables out of a tree.
它所做的就是从 "hre" 中提取出这些变量
It's kind of the same thing as just doing a tree dot get named accounts and HRA dot deployments.
这其实就相当于使用 "hre.getNamedAccounts" 以及 "hre.deployments"
But pulling them out like this means we don't have to add a tree at the beginning anymore.
但使用这种方式的话就不需要在开头加上 "hre." 了
And then additionally, additionally, JavaScript has something called syntactic sugar.
此外呢，JavaScript 还有一种被称为“语法糖”("syntactic sugar")的东西
So instead of doing this on two lines like this,
我们可以不用像这样分成两行来做
we can actually do that whole bit on one line.
而是把这些东西放到一行里面
So instead, we just extrapolate those two variables, right in the function declaration.
我们只需要在函数声明里直接使用这两个变量即可
So this line is the exact same thing as doing this line.
所以这一行，就和这两行所做的事完全相同
This is an asynchronous, nameless function using the arrow notation,
因此这就是一个异步的，无名的，并且使用箭头符号的函数
or working with our deploy scripts here.
用于处理我们的部署脚本
And we're default, exporting it with module dot exports.
并且要在 "module.exports" 中作为默认导出
I don't know that was a lot.
呼，我知道这内容有点多
And another is kind of a lot of syntactic sugar here.
而且这里还使用了一些语法糖
But if that's really confusing for you, just feel free to use the above.
但如果你真的觉得这很让人困惑的话，那么也可以使用上面那种方法
And whenever we refer to get named accounts,
每当我们获取 "getNamedAccounts" 时
you can also just do a three dot get named accounts, or a three dot deployments.
你也可以这么做 "hre.getNamedAccounts" 或者是 "hre.deployments"
So hopefully, that's clear that
希望我已经讲清楚了
this top part is gonna be the same as this bottom part right here,
这里的上半部分和这边的下半部分是完全相同的
whichever one you feel more comfortable working with.
无论你是觉得哪种方式更适合自己
But alright, now that we've gotten all that out of the way, let's continue with the script.
好了，现在我们已经把这些东西都搞清楚了，让我们继续编写脚本吧
So we're using this deployments object,
我们使用了这个 "deployments" 对象
reason this deployments object to get two functions,
通过这个 "deployments" 对象可以获取两个函数
those two functions are going to be the deploy function, and the log function.
这两个函数分别是 "deploy" 函数以及 "log" 函数
So we're gonna say const, deploy log equals deployments.
因此我们要执行 "const  = deployments"
So we're going to pull these two functions out of deployments.
我们要把这两个函数从 "deployments" 中提取出来
And then we're also going to do const Deployer. Equals await, get named accounts.
接着我们要执行 "const  = await getNamedAccounts()"
So we are grabbing this new deploy function, this new log function,
现在我们获取了这个新的 "deploy" 函数以及这个 "log" 函数
and we're grabbing this deployer account
并且我们还获取了部署者的账户
from this weird get named accounts function.
就是通过这个奇怪的 "getNamedAccounts" 函数做到的
What's this get named accounts function,
这个 "getNamedAccounts" 函数到底是什么呢？
this get named accounts is a way for us to get named accounts.
"getNamedAccounts" 就是一个获取 "namedAccounts" 的方法
When working with ethers we saw when working with ethers,
当我们在使用 "ethers" 时
we can actually get our accounts based off of the number in the Account section of each network.
我们可以根据不同网络的 "accounts" 部分中的编号来获取我们的账户
So for example,
举个例子
in this list of private keys, private keys zero private key one private key two,
在这个包含私钥的列表中，有 "privateKey0", "privateKey1", "privateKey2"
it might get a little confusing to remember which ones which
这很容易让人混淆并记不清究竟哪个是哪个
so instead of working like that,
因此，我们不采用这种方式
we can add a section at the bottom called named accounts
而是在底部添加一个名为 "namedAccounts" 的部分
where we can name each one of those spots in the accounts array.
我们可以在里面为 "accounts" 数组中每个位置的账户取一个名字
So we'll do named accounts.
所以我们来写下 "namedAccounts"
And we'll say one of the accounts that will name is going to be named Deployer.
并且我们要把其中一个账户命名为 "deployer"
And we're gonna say by default, the zero with account is going to be Deployer.
并且我们要指定 "default"，即 "accounts" 中的第 0 个就是 "deployer"
We can also specify which number is going to be the deployer account across different chains.
我们也可以指定不同链上的第几个账户为 "deployer"
For example, on Rigby we wanted the deployer account to be the first position,
例如，在 Rinkeby 上如果我们想让位置 1 的账户成为 "deployer"
we could do something like this
我们就可以这么做
or on hard hat, we could do it like this.
或者在 Hardhat 上，我们可以这样做
We can create multiple users. Like for example,
我们还可以创建多个用户，举例来说
if we wanted to do a user for some test or something,
如果我们想为了测试或其他目的而使用 "user"
and we'll just say the default is one or whatever we wanted in here.
我们就可以这样做 "default: 1"，或是任何一个我们想用的编号
So back in our deploy fun me
回到我们的 "deploy-fund-me"
We're going to say we're going to grab that deployer account from our named accounts.
我们就可以说我们通过 "namedAccounts" 获取了 "deployer" 的账户
And then finally, we're going to grab our chain ID
最后，我们要获取我们的 "chainId"
for reasons that will come clear pretty soon.
至于原因很快就会搞清楚的
So we'll do const, chain ID equals network dot config dot chain ID.
我们先写下 "const chainId = network.config.chainId"